COTTON CANDY
솜사탕
Mom.
엄마.
MAY 1975
1975년 5월
TODAY IS CHILDREN'S DAY
오늘은 어린이날입니다
Over here!
여기!
CHILDREN ARE OUR COUNTRY'S TREASURE
어린이는 우리나라의 보물이다
ROMANCE
로맨스
ROMANCE 11
로맨스 11
Look over there.
저기 봐.
Come closer.
가까이 오세요.
Should we pedal all the way there?
거기까지 페달을 밟아야 할까요?
Sure. Let's go.
확신하는. 갑시다.
Pedal.
페달.
-Faster. -Darn it.
-더 빠르게. -젠장.
Hey.
여기요.
-Hey, look out! -What? Over there!
-이봐 요 조심 해요! -무엇? 저기요!
Oh, no. My balloon!
안 돼. 내 풍선!
Ha-young!
하영!
Please help!
도와주세요!
Please help! I need help over here!
도와주세요! 여기 도움이 필요해요!
-Come on. -The students were messing around.
-어서 해봐요. - 학생들이 장난을 치고 있었어요.
And that kid fell into the water.
그리고 그 아이는 물에 빠졌어요.
-My goodness. -That's how they found her.
-이럴 수가. -그래서 그들이 그녀를 찾았어요.
Ma'am.
나는 가지고있다
Excuse me. Ha-young.
실례합니다. 하영.
Ha-young.
하영.
You really scared me today.
오늘 너 정말 무서웠어.
MARCH 1998
1998년 3월
Hey, did you get anything?
야, 뭐 얻은 거 있어?
Brief me.
간단히 설명해주세요.
I haven't seen even a single ant over here.
이곳에서는 개미 한 마리도 본 적이 없습니다 .
Closing news.
종료 소식.
There have been many cases of break-ins
무단 침입 사례가 많이 발생했습니다
at multiplex houses since 1997.
1997년부터 다세대 주택
Women were sexually assaulted and robbed.
여성들은 성폭행을 당하고 강도를 당했습니다.
-This is the Red Cap Incident. -None.
-레드캡 사건입니다. -없음.
It continues to take place.
이런 일이 계속 발생하고 있습니다.
-The police haven't made progress. -How much longer?
-경찰은 진전을 이루지 못했습니다. -얼마나 더 남았나요?
So the public is worried for their safety.
그래서 대중은 그들의 안전을 걱정하고 있습니다.
The police announced that they will reinforce the patrol
경찰이 순찰을 강화하겠다고 밝혔습니다
in alleys and residential areas,
골목 및 주거 지역,
and they would do their best to arrest the culprit.
그리고 그들은 범인을 체포하기 위해 최선을 다할 것입니다 .
Gosh. This is killing me.
맙소사. 정말 죽여주네요.
It's March. How come it's still freezing?
3월이에요. 왜 아직 얼어붙은 걸까요?
It's always cold when we're on a stakeout.
우리가 측량을 할 때는 항상 춥습니다.
Hey.
여기요.
This is the basics of a stakeout.
이것이 측량의 기본이다.
DONGBU POLICE STATION VIOLENT CRIMES ASSISTANT INSPECTOR SONG HA-YOUNG
동부경찰서 강력범죄 부 경위 송하영
I can't believe we can't even go home
우리가 집에 갈 수도 없다는 게 믿기지 않아요
because we have to catch a sex offender.
성범죄자를 잡아야 하기 때문이다.
What is this?
이게 뭔가요?
This has been going on for ten months.
이런 일이 10개월 동안 계속되었습니다.
And there have been 12 victims.
그리고 피해자는 12명입니다.
Besides, this is our job.
게다가 이게 우리 일이에요.
Think about the victims.
피해자들을 생각해 보세요.
Stakeouts are nothing.
측량은 아무것도 아닙니다.
Sure. That's why we must catch him.
확신하는. 그렇기 때문에 우리는 그를 잡아야 합니다.
What if he doesn't show up now that we're waiting for him here?
우리가 여기서 그를 기다리고 있는데 그가 나타나지 않으면 어쩌지 ?
This kind of sting operation has no foundation.
이런 종류의 찌르기 작전 에는 근거가 없습니다.
We'll put this one-dimensional approach behind
우리는 이러한 1차원적 접근 방식을 뒤로 미루겠습니다.
in the 21st century and move forward with more futuristic methods, right?
21세기에는 더욱 미래지향적인 방법으로 나아가겠죠 ?
-What do you mean by futuristic? -I don't know.
-미래적이라는 게 무슨 뜻인가요? -모르겠습니다.
I'm just frustrated. So I'm spitting out ideas.
나는 단지 좌절감을 느낀다. 그래서 아이디어를 뱉어내고 있어요.
I'm frustrated too.
나도 답답하다.
Gosh. You have to speak up now.
이런. 지금 말을 해야 합니다.
I come here every day, and I only saw one cat.
저는 매일 여기에 오는데 고양이 한 마리밖에 못 봤어요.
Right.
오른쪽.
We'll be back tomorrow anyway.
어쨌든 우리는 내일 돌아올 거예요.
-Take out the walkie-talkie. -Okay.
-무전기를 꺼내세요. -좋아요.
Let's see.
어디 보자.
Captain, we'll wrap up for the night.
선장님, 오늘 밤은 마무리하겠습니다.
Captain, it's snowing. Let's call it a night.
선장님, 눈이 오네요. 오늘 밤이라고 부르자.
Okay. Let's wrap it up.
알겠습니다. 마무리하겠습니다.
Come back here tomorrow at 10:00 p.m.
내일 오후 10시에 여기로 다시 오세요
-See you later. -Bye.
-나중에 봐요. -안녕.
Gosh. It's freezing out here. Let's try again tomorrow.
맙소사. 여기는 춥습니다. 내일 다시 시도해 보세요.
-We're wrapping up. Go home. -What?
-마무리하겠습니다. 집에 가세요. - 뭐요?
We can go home?
집에 갈 수 있나요?
It's so cold.
너무 춥다.
Why is it snowing in March?
3월에 왜 눈이 오나요?
-Let's go. -It's too early.
-갑시다. -너무 이르다.
It's 3 a.m. already.
벌써 새벽 3시네요.
Here's what I think.
제 생각은 이렇습니다.
That punk must know that we're here.
그 새끼는 우리가 여기 있다는 걸 알고 있는 게 틀림없어요.
So we should rest up too.
그러니 우리도 쉬어야 해요.
Let's come back when he least expects it.
그가 가장 기대하지 않을 때 돌아오자.
Crime also happens when one least expects it.
범죄는 또한 최소한 예상할 때 발생합니다.
Gosh. I know that.
이런. 나는 그것을 안다.
Who's going to know all the work we do here?
우리가 여기서 하는 모든 일을 누가 알겠어요 ?
We're not making any progress with our investigation.
조사에 아무런 진전이 없습니다 .
Darn it.
젠장.
People just call the cops incompetent.
사람들은 경찰을 무능하다고 부릅니다.
You go home then. I'll stay a bit longer.
그럼 집에 가세요. 좀 더 머물게요.
If you do things on your own,
혼자서 일을 한다면,
Captain Park is going to give me an earful.
박 선장이 나에게 귀를 기울일 것이다 .
Will you stay then?
그럼 계속 계실 거예요?
See you later.
나중에 봐요.
Right.
오른쪽.
Don't tell Captain Park about this.
박 선장에게 이 사실을 말하지 마세요.
Sure. Go home.
확신하는. 집에가.
-Bye. -Okay. See you later.
-안녕. -좋아요. 나중에 봐요.
What do you want to eat?
너 뭐 먹고 싶니?
I'm not going to eat.
나는 먹지 않을 것이다.
Come on. Just show up already.
어서 해봐요. 그냥 나타나세요.
Red Cap.
빨간 모자.
That's not your house.
그곳은 당신 집이 아닙니다.
Come here.
이리 오세요.
It won't take long.
오래 걸리지 않을 것입니다.
Darn it.
젠장.
Hey!
여기요!
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
Come here.
이리 오세요.
Gosh, the weather's so inconsistent.
맙소사, 날씨가 정말 변덕스럽네요.
Why is it raining?
왜 비가 오나요?
-Let's go. -Darn it.
-갑시다. -젠장.
He was just pretending to be Red Cap?
그는 단지 레드캡인 척하고 있었던 것뿐인가요?
He has five priors for rape and assault,
그는 강간과 폭행 전과가 5번 있습니다.
but he has an alibi for every Red Cap Incident.
하지만 그에게는 모든 Red Cap 사건에 대한 알리바이가 있습니다 .
He did it because the red cap
빨간 모자 때문에 그랬어요
makes victims unable to resist due to fear.
피해자가 두려움에 저항할 수 없게 만듭니다 .
DONGBU POLICE STATION
동부경찰서
Take good care of him.
그를 잘 돌봐주세요.
CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIONS
범죄 수사
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
-Why do you think he did it? -What do you mean?
-그가 왜 그런 짓을 했다고 생각해요? -무슨 뜻이에요?
Hey.
여기요.
I don't even want to know what scumbags like him are thinking.
그 사람 같은 쓰레기가 무슨 생각을 하는지 알고 싶지도 않아요 .
Why?
왜?
That's just how they were born.
그것이 바로 그들이 태어난 방법입니다.
He's not thinking.
그는 생각하지 않습니다.
Exactly. We caught him, so why let him mess with you?
정확히. 우리가 그 사람을 잡았는데 왜 그 사람이 당신을 엉망으로 만들도록 놔두나요?
Mess with us?
우리를 엉망으로 만드나요?
With our minds.
우리의 마음으로.
We already have enough to worry about.
우리는 이미 걱정할 만큼 충분합니다.
Once the case is closed, it's wise to not think about it again.
사건이 종결되면 다시는 생각하지 않는 것이 현명합니다.
Do you ever use your brain to think?
당신은 생각하기 위해 두뇌를 사용한 적이 있습니까?
Let's go eat something.
뭔가 먹으러 가자.
What do you want?
당신은 무엇을 원합니까?
-Not coming, right? -No, go ahead.
- 안 오겠죠? -아니야, 계속해.
Copycat crimes imitating Red Cap are running rampant,
레드캡을 모방한 모방범죄가 만연하고 있으며,
adding further complications to the investigation.
조사를 더욱 복잡하게 만들고 있습니다 .
A special promotion offer is on the table for the officer
해당 임원을 위한 특별 프로모션 제안이 준비되어 있습니다.
who catches the culprit, but there aren't enough leads on him.
범인을 잡았 지만 그에 대한 단서가 충분하지 않습니다.
The first Red Cap Incident took place on May 11, 1997.
첫 번째 레드캡 사건은 1997년 5월 11일에 발생했습니다.
He broke into a woman's home in Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul,
그는 서울 동대문구에 있는 한 여성의 집에 침입했다 .
raped her, and fled the scene.
그녀를 강간하고 현장에서 도주했습니다.
To date, 12 sexual assault victims have been reported.
현재까지 12명의 성폭행 피해자가 신고되었습니다.
The culprit is known as "Red Cap"…
범인은 "빨간 모자"로 알려져 있습니다???
-Ms. Choi Hwa-yeon. -Yes.
-Ms. 최화연. -예.
I booked your next appointment
다음 약속을 예약했어요
for the date the doctor suggested.
의사가 제안한 날짜에.
Next time, make sure you come with the father.
다음에는 꼭 아버지와 함께 오세요.
Okay, I will.
알았어, 그럴게.
-Thank you. -Get home safely.
-감사합니다. - 집에 무사히 도착하세요.
Regarding the Red Cap Incident, the police…
레드캡 사건에 대해 경찰은???
They still haven't caught him?
아직도 그를 못 잡았나요?
When will he be caught?
그 사람은 언제 잡힐까요?
Right? It's so scary.
오른쪽? 너무 무섭다.
SERIAL RAPIST RED CAP'S WHEREABOUTS STILL REMAIN UNKNOWN
연쇄강간범 레드캡의 행방은 아직 알려지지 않았다
TURTLE SUPERMARKET
거북이 슈퍼마켓
Mom!
엄마!
My gosh.
이럴수가.
You should've just bought an umbrella.
그냥 우산을 샀어야 했는데.
You're soaked.
흠뻑 젖었군요.
-When did you get here? -Goodness.
-언제 여기 왔니? -선량.
I brought you winter cabbage and green onion kimchi.
겨울배추 와 파김치를 가져왔습니다 .
My gosh, your fridge was a mess.
맙소사, 냉장고가 엉망이었어.
I threw out the spoiled food and cleaned everything.
상한 음식을 버리고 모든 것을 청소했습니다.
I made barley tea too.
보리차도 만들어 봤습니다.
I can do it too. You always do everything and nag me.
나도 할 수 있어요. 넌 항상 별 짓 다 하고 나한테 잔소리만 해.
Go inside.
안으로 들어가세요.
It's raining. You should just sleep here.
비가 온다. 여기서 자면 됩니다.
Don't stay out too late. My goodness.
너무 늦게까지 밖에 머물지 마세요. 이럴 수가.
You're old enough to know that it's a scary world.
당신은 무서운 세상이라는 것을 알 만큼 나이가 들었습니다 .
Just sleep here tonight.
오늘 밤은 그냥 여기서 자세요.
I have to go to work tomorrow.
나는 내일 출근해야 해요.
Take a taxi. I'll give you the money.
택시를 타다. 돈은 내가 줄게
Why waste money when I can take the bus?
버스를 탈 수 있는데 왜 돈을 낭비합니까?
-Forget it. -Wait!
-잊어 버려. -기다리다!
All right.
괜찮은.
Leave the kimchi out for two days.
이틀 동안 김치를 담가두세요.
-That way, it'll age well. -Okay.
-그러면 잘 익을 거예요. -좋아요.
Bye.
안녕.
You're making me uncomfortable. Just go inside.
당신은 나를 불편하게 만들고 있습니다. 그냥 안으로 들어가세요.
Get going.
가야.
I'm not a kid.
나는 어린아이가 아니다.
Bye.
안녕.
-Make sure you take a taxi! -Okay.
-택시를 꼭 타세요! -좋아요.
-Mom! -Yes?
-엄마! -예?
Bye.
안녕.
Bye. Don't forget to lock the door.
안녕. 문을 잠그는 것을 잊지 마세요.
Okay.
좋아요.
It's good.
좋다.
You scared me.
너는 나를 놀래 켰다.
You didn't lock the door.
당신은 문을 잠그지 않았습니다.
The landlord had a break-in.
집주인이 침입을 했습니다.
Make sure you lock the door.
문을 꼭 잠그세요.
When did you get here?
언제 여기 왔니?
-You forgot to take an umbrella, right? -How did you know?
-우산 가져가는 걸 잊었지? -어떻게 알았나요?
The floor was wet, so I wiped it.
바닥이 젖어서 닦아줬어요.
-Right. -I should've picked you up.
-오른쪽. - 내가 당신을 데리러 갔어야 했는데.
Are you having ramyeon?
라면 드시나요?
You want some too?
당신도 좀 원해요?
I should head back out.
나는 다시 밖으로 나가야 한다.
I stopped by to see you before work.
퇴근하기 전에 만나려고 들렀어요.
Can't you just skip work and stay with me tonight?
그냥 일 빼먹고 오늘 밤 나랑 같이 있으면 안 돼 ?
I should work hard to earn more money
돈을 더 벌기 위해 열심히 일해야 해
so that you can live comfortably.
편안하게 살아갈 수 있도록.
I don't want to be alone.
나는 혼자 있고 싶지 않습니다.
Everyone's rejecting me today.
오늘은 다들 나를 거부해요.
-What? -My mom was here.
-무엇? -엄마가 여기 계셨어요.
It's just a food stall. Can't you just hang out with me today?
그냥 음식 파는 곳이에요. 오늘은 나랑 좀 놀아주면 안 돼?
"Just a food stall"?
"그냥 음식 가판대"라고요?
Sorry. Don't get me wrong.
죄송합니다. 오해하지 마세요.
Did you say "just a food stall"?
"그냥 음식 가판대"라고 하셨나요?
Look at you belittling me again.
또 나를 얕보는 것 좀 봐.
What do you mean again?
또 무슨 말이에요?
You get all sensitive whenever I talk about the food stall.
포장마차 얘기를 하면 다들 예민해지시죠 .
Honestly, it makes you look so insecure!
솔직히 말해서, 그것은 당신을 너무 불안해 보이게 만듭니다!
You little…
이 작은???
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
Darn it. What a way to ruin my night.
젠장. 내 밤을 망치는 방법은 무엇입니까?
Breaking news from SBC News.
SBC News의 속보
We've had a few rainy days in a row.
몇일 연속으로 비가 내렸습니다.
At a house in Daebong-dong, Gwangjin-gu, a woman in her twenties was found dead
광진구 대봉동 한 주택에서 20대 여성이 숨진 채 발견
with all of her clothes undressed.
옷을 모두 벗은 채
Police regarded this
경찰은 이를 고려
as a rape and murder case and launched an investigation.
강간 및 살인 사건으로 보고 수사에 착수했습니다.
The police decided to investigate whether this incident
경찰은 이번 사건 여부를 조사하기로 했다
was related to the so-called Red Cap Incident,
일명 레드캡 사건과 관련이 있었고
the sexual assault cases that broke out one after another in Seoul.
서울에서 잇달아 발생한 성폭행 사건
On April 10, a report was made by a woman in her thirties,
4월 10일 30대 여성의 신고가 접수됐는데요 ,
a victim of sexual assault from Hwayang-dong, Gwangjin-gu.
광진구 화양동 성폭력 피해자
May I help you?
도와드릴까요?
Do you have Little Finger?
리틀 핑거(Little Finger)가 있나요?
I'm craving it.
나는 그것을 갈망하고 있습니다.
The case was transferred to the Seoul Metropolitan Police Agency.
사건은 서울지방경찰청으로 이관되었습니다.
Also, the police are…
그리고 경찰은???
TURTLE SUPERMARKET
거북이 슈퍼마켓
It's a snack that looks like a pinky, covered in chocolate.
초콜릿으로 코팅된 새끼손가락 모양의 과자입니다 .
You scared me!
너는 나를 놀래 켰다!
-Look at that. -On the 15th,
-저것 봐. -15일
-Sorry. -a woman in her twenties
-죄송합니다. -20대 여성
-You nearly gave me a heart attack. -was found dead in her house.
-당신은 나에게 심장 마비를 일으킬 뻔했습니다. -그녀의 집에서 숨진 채 발견되었습니다.
I'm a detective.
나는 형사입니다.
-You can relax. -The victim's mother
-편히 쉬셔도 됩니다. -피해자의 어머니
couldn't reach her daughter, so she visited her house
딸과 연락이 닿지 않아 딸이 집을 방문했습니다
-Are you out? I wanted some. -and was the first to see the crime scene.
-나왔어? 나는 약간을 원했다. -범죄 현장을 처음으로 목격했습니다.
You said you're a detective!
당신은 탐정이라고 했잖아요!
Why do you want a chocolate snack like a kid this late at night?
왜 이렇게 늦은 밤 어린아이처럼 초콜렛 과자를 원하는 걸까요 ?
-One second. -The investigation began,
-일초. -조사가 시작되었습니다.
but no witness was found.
그러나 목격자는 발견되지 않았습니다.
These?
이것들?
Yes.
예.
May I have one more?
하나 더 드릴까요?
Thank you.
감사합니다.
CHOI HWA-YEON'S HOME
최화연 집
DO NOT ENTER, UNDER INVESTIGATION
조사 중이므로 들어가지 마세요.
Hey, where have you been?
이봐, 어디 있었어?
Goodness.
선량.
The victim's mother said her daughter came home around 10 p.m. two days ago.
피해자 어머니는 딸이 이틀 전 오후 10시쯤 집에 왔다고 말했습니다.
She couldn't reach her so she came here and made a report.
연락이 안 되서 여기까지 와서 신고를 하더군요.
What about her family?
그녀의 가족은 어떻습니까?
She has a mother,
그녀에게는 어머니가 있고,
but she was in bad condition and was taken to the hospital an hour ago.
그런데 그녀의 상태가 좋지 않아 한 시간 전에 병원으로 이송되었습니다.
She was in awful condition,
그녀의 상태는 매우 나빴습니다.
so I just injected her with a sedative and sleeping agent.
그래서 나는 그녀에게 진정제와 수면제를 주사했습니다.
Whenever he's at the crime scene,
범죄 현장에 있을 때마다
the first thing he does is look for the bereaved family.
그가 가장 먼저 하는 일은 유족을 찾는 것입니다.
If he was staging this, he couldn't do it for so long.
이런 연출을 했다면 그렇게 오랫동안 할 수 없었을 겁니다.
He's an outcast, but he has no idea.
그는 버림받은 사람이지만 전혀 모릅니다.
That's odd too, isn't it?
그것도 이상하지 않나요?
Do you think he doesn't know?
그 사람이 모른다고 생각하나요?
So he does?
그래서 그래요?
Then how can he be so cool about it?
그렇다면 그 사람은 어떻게 그 일에 대해 그렇게 멋질 수 있습니까?
Don't you think he's the one casting us out?
그 사람이 우리를 쫓아내는 사람이라고 생각하지 않나요 ?
What?
무엇?
I heard he got transferred here because he has always been like this.
그는 늘 그랬기 때문에 여기로 전근 왔다고 들었습니다 .
Some say he's the nephew of the commissioner.
어떤 사람들은 그가 국장의 조카라고 말합니다 .
The son-in-law of the brother of the third cousin of his in-law.
사위의 3촌 형제의 사위.
Goodness, word gets around weirdly in this industry.
맙소사, 이 업계에서는 이상한 소문이 돌고 있어요 .
Captain.
선장.
Going back on a case that his direct superior closed.
직속 상관이 종결한 사건을 다시 살펴보겠습니다 .
It's not easy to do that.
그렇게하는 것은 쉽지 않습니다.
Just do your job.
그냥 일을 하세요.
Stop minding something unnecessary.
불필요한 것에 신경쓰지 마세요.
And stop talking to me when I eat.
그리고 밥 먹을 때 나한테 말 걸지 마.
Okay.
좋아요.
-You're home. -Yes.
- 집에 왔어요. -예.
You look tired. You should go to sleep.
좀 피곤해 보이는구나. 이제 가서 자야지.
I will. Goodnight.
그럴게요. 안녕히 주무세요.
SEOUL METROPOLITAN POLICE AGENCY
서울지방경찰청
Gil-pyo.
길표.
-Come on, Gil-pyo. -Stop following me.
- 자, 길표. -따라 다니지 말아 줘.
-Hey, Gil-pyo. -Found it.
-안녕, 길표. -그것을 발견.
This is really important.
이것은 정말 중요합니다.
Hey, Red Cap is turning the world upside down.
안녕하세요, Red Cap이 세상을 뒤집어 놓았습니다.
Why are you here?
당신은 왜 여기에 있습니까?
There will come a day when you'll say I was right.
내가 옳았다고 말할 날이 올 것이다 .
Hey! I'm about to lose my joints running after this case.
여기요! 이 사건 이후로 나는 관절을 잃을 것입니다 .
-That's because of your age. -Darn you. You won't be young forever.
- 나이 때문이군요. -젠장. 당신은 영원히 젊지 않을 것입니다.
CHIEF OF SPECIAL CRIME SQUAD, HEO GIL-PYO
특수수사대장 허길표
We already have Forensics.
우리는 이미 법의학을 갖고 있습니다.
We don't have grounds to establish a Scientific Investigations Team.
과학수사팀을 꾸릴 근거가 없습니다 .
Even an open-hearted guy like me doesn't understand why we need that.
나처럼 마음이 열린 사람이라도 우리에게 그것이 왜 필요한지 이해하지 못합니다.
But the higher-ups? They won't understand.
그런데 윗사람들은요? 그들은 이해하지 못할 것입니다.
I explained it to you so many times.
나는 당신에게 그것을 여러 번 설명했습니다.
You still don't get it?
아직도 이해가 안 되시나요?
We're already short on staff.
우리는 이미 직원이 부족합니다.
Would you spend money to make this team?
이 팀을 만들기 위해 돈을 쓰시겠습니까?
-Think about it. -Come on.
- 생각해 보세요. -어서 해봐요.
"Hey, you rascal!
"야, 이 악당아!
"Go catch another criminal if you have time, you foolish kid."
" 시간 있으면 가서 다른 범인을 잡아라, 멍청한 새끼야."
Wouldn't they say that?
그들은 그렇게 말하지 않겠습니까?
Exactly.
정확히.
We need that team in order to catch one more criminal.
범인을 한 명 더 잡으려면 그 팀이 필요해요 .
Those who have been here for too long don't speak my language.
여기에 너무 오랫동안 있었던 사람들은 내 언어를 사용하지 않습니다.
Goodness, you didn't know?
맙소사, 몰랐나요?
The men who have a say in this, those who have been here for too long,
이에 대해 발언권을 갖고 있는 사람들, 여기에 너무 오랫동안 머물렀던 사람들,
hate unfamiliar methods more than bad methods.
나쁜 방법보다 익숙하지 않은 방법을 더 싫어합니다 .
So you should give up on your dream.
그러니 꿈을 포기해야 합니다.
A dream is meant to be had.
꿈은 꾸기 위한 것입니다.
-Hey, Superintendent Baek. -Hey.
-안녕하세요, 백 총경님. -여기요.
Goodness, what's going on?
맙소사, 무슨 일이에요?
Is he still at it about the scientific investigation?
그는 아직도 과학적인 조사에 전념하고 있나요 ?
Tell me about it. We're all busy, but he must be free.
그것에 대해 말해주세요. 우리는 모두 바쁘지만 그는 한가해야 합니다.
Gil-pyo, do you have to be like this?
길표 꼭 이래야만 해?
My dear Chief Kook Young-soo of Forensics,
사랑하는 법의학 국영수 과장님,
stop talking to me.
나한테 말 좀 그만해.
You can talk directly to Superintendent Baek Jun-sik.
백준식 교육감님과 직접 통화하실 수 있습니다 .
Talk to me about what?
나한테 무슨 얘기를 해?
-My goodness. -Good grief.
-이럴 수가. -맙소사.
Do you know how important profilers are?
프로파일러가 얼마나 중요한지 아시나요?
Yes, I do. Pro fliers, like pilots?
네 저도 그렇습니다. 조종사 같은 프로 플라이어?
If we want to conduct scientific investigations,
과학적 조사를 수행하려면
do we have to get on a plane too?
우리도 비행기를 타야 하나요?
The higher the building goes, the longer its shadow will be.
건물이 높아질수록 그림자가 길어집니다.
Goodness, that's a famous quote from that ancient show, Chief Inspector.
맙소사, 그거 고대 쇼 Chief Inspector에서 나온 유명한 인용문이군요 .
I guess Young-soo isn't that young after all.
아무래도 영수는 그다지 어리지 않은 것 같다 .
With the IMF, the buildings have crashed down.
IMF로 인해 건물이 무너졌습니다.
What shadow? You must have a lot of time on your hands.
무슨 그림자요? 당신은 당신의 손에 많은 시간을 가지고 있어야합니다 .
Listen up.
잘 들어.
Very soon,
금방,
we will see brutal and heinous criminals like the ones in the US.
우리는 미국처럼 잔인하고 흉악한 범죄자들을 보게 될 것입니다 .
These criminals have no motives.
이 범죄자들은 ​​동기가 없습니다.
Then what do we do?
그러면 우리는 무엇을 합니까?
We have to be prepared to deal with criminals like them!
우리는 그들과 같은 범죄자들을 상대할 준비가 되어 있어야 합니다 !
Hey!
여기요!
I can't take this anymore.
나는 이것을 더 이상 참을 수 없습니다.
Are you praying for something big to break out?
뭔가 큰 일이 일어나기를 기도하고 있나요 ?
Why don't you go and pray that a huge case will break out,
가서 큰 사건이 터지길 기도해 보는 건 어때요 ?
into a bigger one, and into an even bigger one?
더 큰 것, 그리고 더 큰 것으로?
That's not what I meant.
그건 나의 의도가 아니 었어.
You know what I mean.
무슨 말인지 아시겠죠?
When's Park Chan-ho game?
박찬호 경기는 언제야?
Young-soo.
영수.
Let's grab one later.
나중에 하나 잡아보자.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
She was pregnant.
그녀는 임신 중이었습니다.
-Pregnant? -Yes, about 14 weeks.
-임신한? - 네, 14주 정도요.
Man, that son of a bitch.
이런, 그 개자식.
She died from asphyxiation due to cervical compression
경추압박으로 인한 질식으로 사망
and mechanical airway obstruction of the nose and mouth.
코와 입의 기계적 기도 폐쇄 .
The estimated time of death
사망 추정 시간
is between 10 p.m. to midnight on the 15th.
15일 밤 10시부터 자정까지입니다 .
The temperature of her rectum shows that it was around 10:30 p.m.
직장 온도를 측정해보니 밤 10시 30분쯤이었습니다.
The contents of her stomach show
그녀의 뱃속의 내용물이 보여요
she ate something within an hour before her death,
그녀는 죽기 한 시간 전에 뭔가를 먹었고 ,
so around 11 p.m.
그래서 밤 11시쯤
Other than the victim's mother,
피해자 어머니 외에
the time of her death coincides with the time of Bang Ki-hoon's visit.
그녀가 사망한 시간은 방기훈이 방문한 시간과 일치한다.
But there's no sign of rape.
하지만 성폭행 흔적은 없습니다.
Wait. What about her clothes?
기다리다. 그녀의 옷은 어때요?
There's no sign of rape, but he undressed her?
강간 흔적은 없는데 옷을 벗겼다고요?
It's Bang Ki-hoon for sure.
바로 방기훈이다.
So Bang Ki-hoon is your friend?
그럼 방기훈이 친구야?
We only went to the same high school.
우리는 같은 고등학교만 다녔어요.
TEMPORARILY CLOSED DUE TO PERSONAL MATTERS
개인적인 문제로 인해 임시 폐쇄되었습니다
Mr. Bang Ki-hoon?
씨. 방기훈?
We're from Dongbu Police Station. Come with us.
저희는 동부경찰서에서 왔습니다. 우리와 함께.
Why should I?
왜 그래야 합니까?
Do you know Choi Hwa-yeon?
최화연을 아시나요?
-She's my girlfriend. -Exactly.
- 그 사람은 내 여자친구예요. -정확히.
You're arrested for the suspicion of Choi Hwa-yeon's murder.
당신은 최화연 살인 혐의로 체포됩니다 .
Murder?
살인?
Murder? What do you mean?
살인? 무슨 뜻이에요?
Is Hwa-yeon dead?
화연이 죽었나요?
We can talk about the details at the station.
자세한 내용은 역에서 얘기할 수 있어요.
You were going to run away?
도망치려고 했어?
Too bad.
안타깝네요.
You missed your window by a close call.
당신은 긴밀한 통화로 인해 창구를 놓쳤습니다.
I'm not running away.
나는 도망치지 않습니다.
Do you have an arrest warrant?
체포 영장이 발부되어 있나요?
Bang Ki-hoon. You have the right to remain silent.
방기훈. 당신은 묵비권을 행사할 권리가 있습니다.
Anything you say can and will be used against you in a court of law.
귀하가 말하는 모든 내용은 법정에서 귀하에게 불리 하게 사용될 수 있습니다 .
You have the right to an attorney.
귀하는 변호사를 선임할 권리가 있습니다.
Hwa-yeon is dead?
화연이 죽었어?
I didn't do it.
나는 그것을하지 않았다.
Yes. Right on cue.
예. 바로 신호에 맞춰요.
That's what everyone says.
모두가 그렇게 말합니다.
I really didn't do it. Why would I…
나는 정말로 그것을하지 않았다. 내가 왜???
All the circumstantial evidence is pointing to you.
모든 정황 증거가 당신을 가리키고 있습니다.
You were at her house at the estimated time of death.
당신은 사망 추정 시간에 그녀의 집에 있었습니다 .
And we also found your fingerprints at her house.
또한 그녀의 집에서 당신의 지문도 발견했습니다.
Why would I kill my girlfriend?
내가 왜 여자친구를 죽였을까?
Exactly.
정확히.
That's what I would like to know too.
그것이 나도 알고 싶습니다.
Why did you kill your girlfriend?
왜 여자친구를 죽였나요?
I didn't kill her.
나는 그녀를 죽이지 않았습니다.
Then where did you go after leaving her house?
그럼 그 집에서 나와서 어디로 갔나요 ?
You didn't work that night.
당신은 그날 밤에 일하지 않았습니다.
You don't have anyone to support your alibi, right?
당신의 알리바이를 뒷받침해 줄 사람은 아무도 없잖아요 ?
I went to the Han River.
한강에 갔어요.
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
At least make it sound believable.
적어도 믿을만한 것처럼 들리도록 만드십시오.
Is that the best you can do?
그게 당신이 할 수 있는 최선인가요?
I'm telling the truth.
나는 진실을 말하고 있습니다.
We fought that night and I wasn't in the mood to work.
그날 밤 우리는 싸웠고 나는 일할 기분이 아니었습니다.
That's it.
그게 다야.
Your motive for killing Choi Hwa-yeon.
최화연 살해 동기.
It was…
그랬어???
a small argument.
작은 논쟁.
Do you kill your girlfriend over some argument you have?
당신은 어떤 논쟁으로 인해 여자친구를 죽입니까 ?
That's the difference between us.
그것이 우리 사이의 차이점입니다.
You're sitting there and I'm sitting here.
당신은 거기 앉아 있고 나는 여기 앉아 있습니다.
We're only one meter apart.
우리는 1미터밖에 떨어져 있지 않습니다.
But there's a huge gap between our humanity.
그러나 우리 인간성 사이에는 커다란 격차가 있습니다 .
Detective.
형사.
I really didn't do it.
나는 정말로 그것을하지 않았다.
Are you…
당신은???
Red Cap?
빨간 모자?
What?
무엇?
We got a report that someone saw a man in a red cap around that time.
그 무렵 누군가 빨간 모자를 쓴 남자를 보았다는 제보를 받았습니다 .
TURTLE SUPERMARKET
거북이 슈퍼마켓
A man without an umbrella was walking, not running.
우산을 쓰지 않은 남자는 달리는 것이 아니라 걷고 있었다.
I just thought that it was because he was wearing a cap.
그냥 모자를 쓰고 있어서 그런 줄 알았습니다 .
Was it red?
빨간색이었나요?
I think it was.
그랬던 것 같아요.
-A red cap? -Yes.
-빨간 모자요? -예.
Do you remember anything else about him?
그에 대해 또 기억나는 게 있나요?
As for his height…
그의 키는???
I'm not sure.
잘 모르겠습니다.
Anyway, he was pretty short like a girl.
어쨌든 그 사람은 여자아이처럼 키가 꽤 작았거든요.
Detective.
형사.
What can I do to make you believe me?
당신이 나를 믿게 만들려면 어떻게 해야 할까요?
Show me evidence you didn't do it. Then I'll believe you.
당신이 그러지 않았다는 증거를 보여주세요. 그러면 나는 당신을 믿을 것입니다.
We only believe in evidence.
우리는 증거만을 믿습니다.
But you don't have evidence. Do you?
하지만 당신은 증거가 없습니다. 당신은?
The door.
문.
The door wasn't locked.
문은 잠겨 있지 않았습니다.
Think carefully before you speak.
말하기 전에 신중하게 생각하십시오.
This statement could work against you.
이 진술은 당신에게 불리할 수 있습니다.
I'm not the one.
나는 그 사람이 아니다.
You have a record for assault.
폭행 전과가 있습니다.
And pretending you left the gang with that food stall.
그리고 당신이 그 음식 가판대에서 갱단을 떠난 척합니다 .
I'm not pretending. I'm done with that life.
나는 척하지 않습니다. 나는 그 삶을 끝냈습니다.
Whatever it is, I don't care.
그것이 무엇이든 나는 상관하지 않습니다.
But people like you get hot-tempered just like now.
그런데 당신 같은 사람들은 지금처럼 화를 잘 냅니다.
And when you do,
그리고 그렇게 할 때,
you unintentionally end up hurting people, right?
의도치 않게 사람에게 상처를 주게 되는 거죠?
Just be honest.
솔직 해져.
I don't kill people.
나는 사람을 죽이지 않습니다.
Are you a gang member who has a heart?
마음이 있는 갱단원이신가요?
Did your dead girlfriend know
죽은 여자친구는 알고 있었나요?
that you used to be in a gang?
너 예전에 갱단에 있었다고?
Then did you know…
그럼 알고 계셨나요???
that Choi Hwa-yeon was pregnant?
최화연 임신했다고?
What do you mean?
무슨 뜻이에요?
Given that you were dating,
데이트를 했다는 점을 고려하면,
you two kept a lot of secrets from each other.
너희 둘은 서로에게 많은 비밀을 지켰다 .
I'm telling you.
나는 당신에게 말하고있다.
You can't just rely on tangible evidence.
확실한 증거에만 의존할 수는 없습니다.
Well, without the evidence, we'd be shooting blind.
글쎄요, 증거가 없다면 우리는 맹목적으로 총격을 가할 것입니다.
Then what do you suggest?
그러면 무엇을 제안하시나요?
What should we rely on?
우리는 무엇을 의지해야 합니까?
-How they prepared to commit crimes. -Right.
- 범죄를 저지르기 위해 어떻게 준비했는지. -오른쪽.
And how and why they committed crimes.
그리고 그들이 범죄를 저지른 방법과 이유.
And how the corpses were handled.
그리고 시체를 어떻게 처리했는지.
We should be studying the entire process.
우리는 전체 과정을 연구해야 합니다.
-Right. And scientifically too. -Yes.
-오른쪽. 그리고 과학적으로도요. -예.
Science.
과학.
Come on. Stop talking about science.
어서 해봐요. 과학 얘기는 그만하세요.
Hold on.
기다리다.
Do you have to get the license to be a pilot or whatever that's called?
조종사가 되려면 자격증을 취득해야 합니까 ?
What? Why are you laughing?
무엇? 왜 웃어요?
Are you Choi Bool-am or what? "Pilot"?
당신이 최불암인가요? "조종사"?
-Gosh. You're so frustrating. -You're frustrating.
-맙소사. 정말 답답하시군요. - 답답하시군요.
It's not a pilot. It's a profiler.
조종사가 아닙니다. 프로파일러입니다.
-Right. A profil… -A profiler.
-오른쪽. 프로필??? -프로파일러.
A profiler.
프로파일러.
All right. I'm sorry.
괜찮은. 죄송합니다.
By the way, who's going to do that?
그런데 누가 그런 일을 하게 될까요?
I know just the guy.
나는 그 사람을 알고 있습니다.
He's more stubborn than I am.
그 사람은 나보다 더 고집이 세다.
-Gosh. He sounds like trouble. -Goodness.
-맙소사. 그는 문제가 있는 것처럼 들린다. -선량.
TEMPORARILY CLOSED DUE TO PERSONAL MATTERS
개인사정으로 인해 임시 휴업합니다
Bang Ki-hoon. Did you really do it?
방기훈. 정말 그랬나요?
Gosh, he's taking a while.
맙소사, 시간이 좀 걸리네요.
There were a lot of petty thieves in that neighborhood.
그 동네에는 좀도둑이 많았어요 .
The landlord on the second floor was robbed of their valuables too.
2층 집주인 도 귀중품을 강탈당했습니다.
When?
언제?
About a month ago.
약 일 개월 전.
Their house had a smart door lock.
그들의 집에는 스마트 도어락이 있었습니다.
When did you check that?
그건 언제 확인하셨나요?
Wait. Are you going there?
기다리다. 거기 가시나요?
Gosh. You really shouldn't.
이런. 정말 그러시면 안됩니다.
You killed a person. You bastard.
당신은 사람을 죽였습니다. 이 개자식.
You scum.
당신은 쓰레기입니다.
You should feel guilty.
죄책감을 느껴야합니다.
What?
무엇?
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
Getting a confession out of him.
그에게서 자백을 받는 것.
Close the door.
문을 닫다.
We're not done, you piece of trash.
아직 안 끝났어, 쓰레기야.
You jerk.
멍청 아.
What's the problem? What is it?
뭐가 문제 야? 그것은 무엇입니까?
Do you think this kind of confession is valid?
이런 고백이 타당하다고 생각하시나요 ?
Don't act all righteous and lecture me.
옳게 행동하지 말고 나에게 강의하지 마십시오.
Get back to work.
다시 일하세요.
This is my work too.
이것도 내 일이에요.
Gosh. Come on.
이런. 어서 해봐요.
Get out.
나가세요.
He can't even give me his alibi right now.
그는 지금 나에게 알리바이를 줄 수도 없습니다.
Why? Because he killed her.
왜? 왜냐하면 그가 그녀를 죽였기 때문이죠.
You know he was there at the estimated time of death.
당신은 그가 사망 추정 시간에 그곳에 있었다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
Your friend from school fought with Choi Hwa-yeon that day.
그날 학교 친구가 최화연이랑 싸웠어요.
He didn't call her for a few days, so he had no idea she was dead.
그는 며칠 동안 그녀에게 전화를 하지 않았기 때문에 그녀가 죽은 줄도 몰랐습니다.
-You think that makes any sense? -She was pregnant.
- 그게 말이 된다고 생각하시나요? - 임신 중이셨어요.
Bang Ki-hoon might not be the culprit.
방기훈이 범인이 아닐 수도 있다.
You think murderers have mercy?
살인자에게 자비가 있다고 생각하시나요?
They don't.
그들은 그렇지 않습니다.
But it was too bad for him.
하지만 그에게는 너무 안타까운 일이었습니다.
He didn't even know she was pregnant.
그는 그녀가 임신했다는 사실조차 몰랐습니다.
Hey.
여기요.
She must have hidden the fact that she was pregnant for a reason.
그녀는 어떤 이유에서인지 임신 사실을 숨겼던 게 틀림없다 .
Even if I want to be lenient with him, I can't.
내가 그 사람에게 관대해지고 싶어도 그럴 수가 없어요.
Even his motive is crystal clear.
그의 동기조차도 분명합니다.
These gangsters will never learn.
이 갱스터들은 결코 배우지 못할 것입니다.
They get hot-tempered and cause trouble.
그들은 화를 잘 내고 문제를 일으킨다.
They are dumb to stage a perfect crime,
완전범죄를 저지르기엔 멍청한 놈들
but they don't want to serve time.
하지만 그들은 시간을 보내고 싶어하지 않습니다.
But you still want to believe that guy?
그런데 아직도 그 사람을 믿고 싶나요?
That's not what I'm saying.
내가 말하는 것은 그게 아니다.
I just want to find definitive evidence.
다만 확실한 증거를 찾고 싶을 뿐입니다.
You said you weren't friends with him.
그 사람이랑 친구가 아니라고 했잖아.
Then listen up.
그럼 잘 들어보세요.
Those bastards…
그 새끼들???
don't deserve to be called human.
인간이라 불릴 자격이 없어.
And beating those scumbags is the fastest and the easiest way.
그리고 그 쓰레기들을 물리치는 것이 가장 빠르고 쉬운 방법입니다.
But this is still wrong.
그러나 이것은 여전히 ​​잘못된 것입니다.
I know why you got kicked out of Jungbu Police Station,
중부경찰서에서 쫓겨난 이유를 알겠다
but don't try to police your supervisors by nitpicking us.
하지만 우리를 따돌림으로써 감독관을 단속하려고 하지는 마세요 .
Just get out there and catch criminals.
그냥 나가서 범죄자를 잡으세요.
Just go out there. You have a lot of work to do.
그냥 나가세요. 당신은 할 일이 많습니다.
Hey.
여기요.
Investigate him in connection with the Red Cap case.
레드캡 사건과 관련해 그를 조사해 보세요 .
Yes, sir.
알겠습니다.
But he didn't rape her, and the method is different.
하지만 그는 그녀를 강간하지 않았고 방법도 다릅니다.
Such perverted acts are no different from rape.
이런 변태적인 행위는 강간과 다르지 않습니다.
Wait, where are you going?
잠깐, 어디로 가는 거야?
To find evidence.
증거를 찾으려면.
My goodness.
이럴 수가.
The first reason why Ki-hoon isn't the killer.
기훈이 살인자가 아닌 첫 번째 이유 .
There are signs of forced entry.
강제 진입 흔적이 있습니다.
The second reason why he isn't the killer.
그가 살인자가 아닌 두 번째 이유
Choi Hwa-yeon was pregnant.
최화연이 임신했다.
Then did you know…
그럼 알고 계셨나요???
that Choi Hwa-yeon was pregnant?
최화연 임신했다고?
But he didn't know, and he denied all charges.
그러나 그는 몰랐고 모든 혐의를 부인했습니다.
The first reason why Ki-hoon is the killer.
기훈이 살인범인 첫 번째 이유 .
His prints and blood were found at the scene.
그의 지문과 혈액이 현장에서 발견되었습니다.
The second reason why he is the killer.
그가 살인자인 두 번째 이유.
The estimated time of death also matches.
사망 추정 시간도 일치합니다.
That bastard…
그 새끼???
Your little friend from school
학교에서 온 작은 친구
fought with Choi Hwa-yeon that day.
그날 최화연과 싸웠습니다.
Clear motive. Reason number three.
명확한 동기. 세 번째 이유.
Show me evidence you didn't do it. Then I'll believe you.
당신이 그러지 않았다는 증거를 보여주세요. 그러면 나는 당신을 믿을 것입니다.
He has no alibi.
그에게는 알리바이가 없습니다.
Reason number four.
네 번째 이유.
He entered through the door instead of the window.
창문이 아닌 문으로 들어왔습니다 .
I should really move.
정말 움직여야 해요.
Petty thieves are one thing, but someone died.
사소한 도둑도 하나이지만 누군가가 죽었습니다.
I'm so terrified I can't live here anymore.
너무 무서워서 여기서 더 이상 살 수 없어요.
Even I'm this scared.
나조차도 이 정도는 겁이 난다.
So I'm worried the house won't sell.
그래서 집이 안 팔릴까봐 걱정이에요.
Who else had break-ins in this area?
이 지역에 또 누가 침입했습니까?
There were three to four other cases, just counting the ones I heard of.
그 밖에도 제가 들은 것까지 포함해서 3~4가지 사례가 더 있었습니다 .
That's the problem.
그것이 문제이다.
The stolen goods aren't that valuable, so the cops don't care.
훔친 물건은 그다지 귀중하지 않기 때문에 경찰은 신경 쓰지 않습니다.
It's been so long.
너무 오랜만이에요.
If it was a rich family, the thief would be in jail.
만약 부유한 집이었다면 도둑은 감옥에 갇혔을 것입니다.
Was there another break-in downstairs before this incident?
이 사건 이전에도 아래층에 침입이 있었나요 ?
No, not that I know of.
아니요, 제가 아는 바는 아닙니다.
Okay, thank you for your cooperation.
알겠습니다. 협조해 주셔서 감사합니다.
Detective.
형사.
Can you catch the thief who stole my jewelry
내 보석을 훔친 도둑을 잡을 수 있나요?
while tracking down the jerk who killed the lady downstairs?
아래층 아줌마를 죽인 멍청이를 추적하는 동안 ?
Okay. Just a moment, please.
좋아요. 잠시만 기다려주세요.
Ma'am, these numbers here.
부인, 여기 숫자가 있습니다.
Did you write them?
당신이 썼나요?
What is that?
저게 뭐에요?
My goodness.
이럴 수가.
Why would I doodle on the wall? I'm not a kid.
내가 왜 벽에 낙서를 하겠는가? 나는 어린아이가 아니다.
Maybe my granddaughters wrote them when they came over.
어쩌면 내 손녀들이 왔을 때 썼을 수도 있습니다 .
Anyway, thank you.
아무튼 감사 해요.
Detective, please catch that thief.
형사님, 저 도둑을 꼭 잡아주세요.
THEFT REPORT
도난 신고
Five cases were reported in total.
총 5건의 사례가 보고되었습니다.
There was a break-in every two weeks until three months ago.
3개월 전까지만 해도 2주에 한 번씩 침입이 있었어요 .
The last one was the two-story house at 214 Daebong-dong?
마지막은 대봉동 214번지 2층집이었죠?
Yes, this jerk is clever.
응, 이 멍청이는 영리해.
He never breaks into houses with men.
그는 결코 남자들과 함께 집에 침입하지 않습니다.
And only steals cheap items.
그리고 값싼 물건만 훔칩니다.
It's so petty that there are no leads on him whatsoever.
너무 사소해서 그에 대한 단서가 전혀 없습니다.
So Dongbu Police Station has given up.
그래서 동부경찰서는 포기했습니다.
We've enhanced patrols in the area.
우리는 해당 지역의 순찰을 강화했습니다.
Thankfully, it's been quiet since then.
다행히 그 이후로는 조용했어요.
Okay, thank you.
좋아 감사합니다.
DAEBONG PRECINCT
대봉지구
Daebong-dong, 183-10.
대봉동 183-10
The number, 233.
번호는 233입니다.
Hey! Who are you?
여기요! 누구세요?
-What are you doing? -Hold on!
-뭐하세요? -기다리다!
-Ma'am, hold on! -Why are you lurking around?
- 부인, 잠깐만요! -왜 숨어 지내는 걸까요?
-I'm a police officer! -Why? What?
-나는 경찰이다! -왜? 무엇?
I'm a police officer.
저는 경찰관입니다.
Then why didn't you ring the doorbell?
그럼 왜 초인종을 누르지 않았나요?
Why did you lurk around my house? It looked so suspicious.
왜 우리 집 주변에 숨어 있었나요? 너무 의심스러워 보였습니다.
-My gosh. -I'm sorry. It was getting late.
-이럴수가. -죄송합니다. 점점 늦어지고 있었어요.
What can I do for you?
내가 당신을 위해 무엇을 할 수?
I have a few questions.
몇 가지 질문이 있습니다.
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
Do you happen to know what these numbers are for?
이 숫자가 무엇을 위한 것인지 아시나요 ?
That's not my address.
그건 내 주소가 아니야.
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
-Mom. -Yes?
-엄마. -예?
Why did you come out?
왜 나왔나요?
Who's in your family?
당신의 가족은 누구입니까?
Me and my kids. Just the three of us.
나와 내 아이들. 우리 셋뿐이에요.
What about your husband?
너의 남편은 어때?
Why do you ask?
왜 물어보나요?
I'm investigating the area.
그 지역을 조사하고 있어요.
We don't live together.
우리는 함께 살지 않습니다.
I see. I'm sorry.
알겠어요. 죄송합니다.
You don't think your kids wrote the numbers, do you?
당신은 당신의 아이들이 숫자를 썼다고 생각하지 않습니까 ?
They're not tall enough to reach that high.
그들은 그 높이에 도달할 만큼 키가 크지 않습니다.
I see.
알겠어요.
Thank you for your cooperation.
도와 주셔서 감사합니다.
Sure. Come on. Let's go back inside.
확신하는. 어서 해봐요. 다시 안으로 들어가자.
Bye, Mr. Policeman.
안녕하세요, 경찰관님.
-Hurry, go inside. -Goodbye.
-어서 들어가세요. -안녕히 가세요.
-Gosh, this neighborhood. -Sorry.
- 맙소사, 이 동네. -죄송합니다.
Daebong-dong, 190-3.
대봉동 190-3
The number, 22.
번호는 22입니다.
Who do you live with?
누구와 함께 살고 있나요?
Just me and my sibling. Why do you ask?
나와 내 동생뿐이에요. 왜 물어보나요?
Your sibling? Sister or brother?
당신의 형제? 자매인가, 아니면 형제인가?
Sister.
자매.
Who do you live with?
누구와 함께 살고 있나요?
I live alone.
난 혼자 사는.
My mom. It's just the two of us.
우리 엄마. 우리 둘뿐이에요.
The number is on every third house.
번호는 세 번째 집마다 있습니다.
Who do you live with?
누구와 함께 살고 있나요?
I live with my wife. What's this about?
나는 아내와 함께 살고 있습니다. 무엇에 대한 거지?
-Who is it? -Hello.
-누구예요? -안녕하세요.
My wife and I live here with our ten-year-old son.
제 아내와 저는 열 살 된 아들과 함께 이곳에 살고 있습니다.
Choi Hwa-yeon's landlord's house had 233.
최화연 집주인 집은 233호였습니다.
The house with two kids also had 233 written on the wall.
두 아이가 있는 집의 벽에는 233이라고 적혀 있었습니다.
These numbers seem random.
이 숫자는 무작위인 것 같습니다.
What could they mean?
무슨 뜻인가요?
Gosh, that bastard. He should watch out.
맙소사, 그 놈. 그는 조심해야 해요.
Maybe my granddaughters wrote them when they came over.
아마도 내 손녀들이 집에 왔을 때 썼을 것입니다 .
Me and my kids. Just the three of us.
나와 내 아이들. 우리 셋뿐이야.
DO YOUR DUTY
당신의 의무를 다하십시오
The restaurants in this area.
이 지역의 레스토랑들입니다.
How many of them offer delivery?
그 중 배달 서비스를 제공하는 곳은 몇 곳인가요?
-Delivery? -See these numbers?
-배달? - 이 숫자 보여요?
What is this?
이게 뭔가요?
It shows who lives in the house.
집에 누가 살고 있는지 보여줍니다.
Two for women. Three for kids. And one…
여성용 2개. 아이들을 위한 세 가지. 그리고 하나???
means an adult male.
성인 남성을 의미합니다.
The culprit avoided houses where men live.
범인은 남자들이 사는 집을 피했다.
He only targeted houses with women and kids.
그는 여성과 아이들이 있는 집만을 표적으로 삼았습니다 .
But what does that have to do with delivery?
그런데 그게 배달과 무슨 상관이 있는 걸까요 ?
It has to be someone with a job…
꼭 직업이 있는 사람이겠죠???
that can figure out who lives in the house.
그 집에 누가 살고 있는지 알아낼 수 있어요 .
BREAKING NEWS
긴급 속보
Breaking news.
속보.
The serial rapist known as "Red Cap,"
'레드캡'으로 알려진 연쇄 성폭행범
who has made women living in Seoul fall in deep terror,
서울에 사는 여성들을 깊은 공포에 빠지게 만든
was arrested last night.
어젯밤에 체포되었습니다.
You're heading out already?
벌써 나가는 중이신가요?
-Yes. -Dongbu Police Station officers
-예. -동부경찰서 직원
-Gosh, isn't that your district? -went to the scene after a report
- 맙소사, 거기가 당신 구역 아닌가요? -신고 후 현장으로 이동
and arrested the suspect.
그리고 용의자를 체포했습니다.
The suspect was caught red-handed, wearing his red cap.
피의자는 빨간 모자를 쓰고 적발됐다.
He admitted all charges and confessed he was the culprit
모든 혐의를 인정 하고 자신이 범인임을 자백했습니다
of the Red Cap serial murder case.
레드캡 연쇄살인사건
Do you admit to everything?
다 인정하시나요?
-A comment, please. -Anything to say to the victim's family?
-댓글 부탁드립니다. -피해자 가족들에게 하고 싶은 말이 있다면?
-A comment! -Move back!
-댓글! -뒤로가!
-Look here! -Say something!
-이봐! -말 좀 해봐!
-Why did you do it? -How do you feel now?
- 왜 그랬어요? -당신은 지금 기분이 어떻게?
-Just a comment! -Wait!
-댓글만요! -기다리다!
Do you admit to all charges?
모든 혐의를 인정하시나요?
-Just a comment!
-댓글만요!
Unlike the previous cases that took place in the victims' homes.
피해자의 집에서 발생한 이전 사건과는 다릅니다 .
-This incident took place… -How dare you smirk? Is this funny?
-이 사건이 일어났나요??? -어떻게 감히 웃으실 수 있나요? 이거 웃기나요?
Request an arrest warrant.
체포영장을 요청하세요.
Yes, sir.
알겠습니다.
Detective, it really wasn't me.
형사님, 정말 제가 아니었습니다.
Why would I kill Hwa-yeon?
내가 왜 화연을 죽이겠는가?
-Sit down. -That scum.
-앉아. - 그 쓰레기.
Song Ha-young, right?
송하영 맞죠?
The culprit picked the lock.
범인은 자물쇠를 골랐다.
Look, these numbers…
보세요, 이 숫자는???
Your friend already confessed.
네 친구는 이미 고백했어.
Goodness. Should I go to a temple somewhere and pray?
선량. 어딘가 절 에 가서 기도해야 할까요 ?
Talk about bad timing.
나쁜 타이밍에 대해 이야기하십시오.
How could he kill his own girlfriend?
그는 어떻게 자신의 여자친구를 죽일 수 있었습니까?
It really wasn't me. Please believe me.
정말 내가 아니었어요. 제발 나를 믿어 줘.
Hey, I've seen plenty of scumbags
아, 난 쓰레기 같은 놈들을 많이 봤어
who killed their wives, daughters,
아내와 딸을 죽인 자,
and even their own parents in the spur of the moment.
심지어 순간적으로는 자신의 부모까지도요 .
A girlfriend? That's nothing.
여자친구요? 그건 별거 아니야.
Goodness, me and my bad luck.
맙소사, 나와 내 불운.
I caught a murderer,
살인범을 잡았어요
but that bastard is getting all the spotlight now.
그런데 그 놈이 지금 주목을 받고 있어요 .
They only care because she was pregnant.
그들은 그녀가 임신했기 때문에 관심을 갖습니다.
Why did he take her clothes off?
그는 왜 그녀의 옷을 벗겼는가?
I guess he's a twisted pervert.
아무래도 그 사람은 뒤틀린 변태인 것 같아요.
You expect me to know his sexual preferences too?
내가 그 사람 성적 취향도 알 거라고 생각하는 거야?
If you're that curious, just ask his friend over there.
그렇게 궁금하면 저기 있는 친구한테 물어보세요.
That guy isn't the culprit.
그 사람은 범인이 아니예요.
Get up and follow me.
일어나서 나를 따라오세요.
Going to the Special Crime Squad?
특수수사대에 가시나요?
Why would I go there? We're the ones who caught him.
내가 왜 거기로 갈까요? 그를 잡은 것은 우리입니다.
All right.
괜찮은.
The lucky ones always fall on a pile of gold.
운이 좋은 사람은 항상 금더미 위에 떨어지게 됩니다.
Hey!
여기요!
I know you're Red Cap.
나는 당신이 레드캡이라는 것을 알고 있습니다.
Why?
왜?
Do you wish I wasn't?
내가 아니길 바라나요?
You're nothing but a little puppy.
당신은 작은 강아지에 지나지 않습니다.
Don't try to act tough.
터프한 척 하려고 하지 마세요.
That guy isn't the culprit.
그 사람은 범인이 아니예요.
Is Bang Ki-hoon the real culprit?
진짜 범인은 방기훈인가?
His eyes weren't that of a criminal's eyes though.
그의 눈은 범죄자의 눈 이 아니었습니다 .
Detective.
형사.
Please…
제발???
Do everything you can to catch the guy
그 사람을 잡기 위해 최선을 다하세요
who killed my daughter.
내 딸을 죽인 사람.
Choi Hwa-yeon's boyfriend, Bang Ki-hoon.
최화연의 남자친구 방기훈.
He's the culprit.
그 사람이 범인이에요.
Did you say "boyfriend"?
"남자친구"라고 하셨나요?
Hwa-yeon had a boyfriend?
화연에게 남자친구가 있었나요?
She hid her pregnancy and even the fact that she had a boyfriend.
임신 사실은 물론 남자친구가 있다는 사실도 숨겼습니다 .
Is Bang Ki-hoon the real culprit?
진짜 범인은 방기훈인가?
Goodness me.
맙소사.
Of all the things to take after me, it had to be my bad luck with men.
나를 따라야 할 모든 것 중에서 그것은 남자와의 불운이었습니다.
I'm so sorry, Hwa-yeon.
정말 미안해, 화연아.
I'm sorry, Hwa-yeon.
미안해, 화연아.
I should have stayed with her that day.
나는 그날 그녀와 함께 있어야 했어요.
She asked me to sleep over.
그녀는 나에게 자고 싶다고 요청했습니다.
She offered, but I declined.
그녀는 제안했지만 나는 거절했습니다.
It's not your fault.
그것은 당신의 잘못이 아닙니다.
I should have died instead of Hwa-yeon.
화연 대신 내가 죽었어야 했는데.
My gosh, Hwa-yeon.
맙소사, 화연아.
Goodness.
선량.
SOONAE HOSPITAL EMERGENCY ROOM
순애병원 응급실
CHIEF OF FORENSICS KOOK YOUNG-SOO
국영수 포렌식 실장
Hello?
안녕하세요?
Chief, this is Ha-young.
실장님, 하영이에요.
Yes?
예?
I have a favor to ask.
부탁드릴 게 있어요.
-You're here. -Yes.
-너 여기 있네. -예.
Here.
여기.
Gosh.
이런.
Where is it?
어디입니까?
They may have missed something the first time.
그들은 처음에 뭔가를 놓쳤을 수도 있습니다 .
The prints were only on the cup.
지문은 컵에만 있었습니다.
If Bang Ki-hoon cleaned it all up, why would he have left just this?
방기훈이 다 정리했다면 왜 이것만 남겼을까?
Everything matches.
모든 것이 일치합니다.
From his fingerprints, bloodstain, and time of death.
그의 지문, 혈흔, 사망 시간 등을 통해 알 수 있다.
He even confessed.
그는 심지어 고백했다.
That's true, but…
사실이지만???
You just got to Dongbu Station.
방금 동부역에 도착했어요.
Will you be okay?
괜찮으시겠어요?
I came because you asked,
당신이 부탁해서 왔어요.
but just as a case is important,
하지만 사건이 중요하듯이
-relationships are also-- -You're right.
-관계도-- - 네 말이 맞아.
But catching the culprit is the most important.
하지만 범인을 잡는 것이 가장 중요합니다.
You never give in to anything.
당신은 아무것도 포기하지 않습니다.
I heard the suspect is your friend.
용의자는 당신 친구라고 들었습니다.
Did you do a background check?
신원조사를 해보셨나요?
That's nonsense.
그건 말도 안되는 소리입니다.
I call it "having interest."
나는 그것을 '관심이 있다'고 부른다.
We're basically strangers.
우리는 기본적으로 낯선 사람입니다.
Being friends doesn't change anything.
친구가 된다고 달라지는 건 없습니다.
As I told you earlier…
아까 말했듯이???
All right, I got it.
알겠습니다. 알겠습니다.
I'm good with just our relationship.
나는 우리 관계만으로도 괜찮습니다.
That's why I couldn't refuse. You know that, right?
그렇기 때문에 거절할 수 없었습니다. 그거 알지?
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Express it a little for me then.
그럼 나한테 좀 표현해봐.
-Here? -No, forget it.
-여기? -아니요, 잊어버리세요.
The fact the culprit was calm enough to erase his footprints and fingerprints
범인은 자신의 발자국과 지문을 지울 정도로 침착했다는 사실
means that the crime was most likely planned.
이는 범죄가 계획되었을 가능성이 높다는 것을 의미합니다.
A woman living alone in a one-bedroom…
원룸에 혼자 사는 여자???
The killer may have been hiding and waiting.
범인은 숨어서 기다리고 있었을지도 모릅니다 .
Either underneath this bed…
이 침대 밑인가요???
or behind here.
아니면 여기 뒤에.
Hey. Have you gone mad?
여기요. 화났어?
Damn it.
젠장.
Why did you ask to run prints on a case that's closed?
종결된 케이스에 대해 인쇄를 실행해 달라고 요청한 이유는 무엇입니까 ?
Why?
왜?
You said that Bang Ki-hoon isn't your friend!
방기훈은 친구가 아니라고 하더군요!
That's not the reason.
그것은 이유가 아닙니다.
Friend or not. This case is over.
친구든 아니든. 이 사건은 끝났습니다.
Bang Ki-hoon confessed!
방기훈이 고백했다!
That's because you forced a confession--
자백을 강요했기 때문이죠..
You're a complete lunatic, aren't you?
당신은 완전 미치광이군요, 그렇죠?
Is Bang Ki-hoon stupid?
방기훈은 바보인가?
Why would he lie?
그는 왜 거짓말을 했을까요?
He did say he didn't kill her.
그는 그녀를 죽이지 않았다고 말했습니다.
Damn you, you crazy bastard.
젠장, 미친 놈아.
Is it your hobby to screw your superiors over?
상사를 엿먹이는 게 취미인가요 ?
What's the problem?
뭐가 문제 야?
I'm just saying Bang Ki-hoon may not be the culprit.
단지 방기훈이 범인이 아닐 수도 있다는 뜻이다 .
If he's not…
만약 그렇지 않다면???
If Bang Ki-hoon isn't the culprit…
방기훈이 범인이 아니라면???
What are you going to do about it?
그것에 대해 무엇을 할 건가요?
If that's the case, we'll have a bigger problem.
그렇다면 우리는 더 큰 문제에 직면하게 될 것입니다.
You know that.
당신은 그것을 알고 있습니다.
-Know what? You bastard! -Captain!
-무엇을 알고? 이 개자식! -선장!
-You know? -Calm down.
-알잖아? -진정하다.
-You know nothing! -Please!
-당신은 아무것도 몰라! -제발!
Step outside for a moment, please!
잠시만 밖으로 나가주세요!
Calm down, Captain.
진정하세요, 캡틴.
Hey!
여기요!
You'd better fix your attitude if you want to keep this career.
이 경력을 유지하고 싶다면 태도를 고치는 것이 좋습니다 .
You got it?
맞아요?
DETECTIVE DIVISION
탐정과
-Yes? -Inspector Song Ha-young?
-예? -송하영 경위?
I'm calling to notify you that the fingerprint results are in.
지문 결과가 나왔음을 알려드리려고 전화드렸습니다 .
But we were unable to confirm the identity.
그러나 신원을 확인할 수 없었습니다 .
I understand the frustration,
답답함은 이해하지만,
but you have to accept the outcome.
하지만 결과를 받아들여야 합니다.
-You're here. -Yes.
-너 여기 있네. -예.
My instincts are telling me otherwise.
내 본능은 그렇지 않다고 말하고 있습니다.
I know we can't take a detective's instincts lightly.
나는 우리가 탐정의 본능을 가볍게 여겨서는 안 된다는 것을 안다 .
But we have definite evidence and his confession too.
하지만 확실한 증거 와 그의 자백도 있습니다 .
That's true, but…
사실이지만???
The fact that the victim's wallet disappeared,
피해자의 지갑이 사라졌다는 사실 ,
how she was left undressed,
그녀가 어떻게 옷을 벗은 채 방치됐는지,
and the trace of breaking in.
그리고 침입의 흔적
And the suspicious numbers on the walls.
그리고 벽에 붙은 의심스러운 숫자들
All those things are bothering me.
그 모든 것들이 나를 괴롭히고 있어요.
If it were a premeditated crime,
만약에 계획된 범죄였다면,
why was she left undressed?
그녀는 왜 옷을 벗은 채 방치됐나요?
The killer must've been busy covering up.
범인은 은폐하느라 바빴나 봐요.
Have you heard about profilers?
프로파일러에 대해 들어보셨나요?
We call them criminal behavioral analysts.
우리는 그들을 범죄 행동 분석가라고 부릅니다.
You have all the qualifications…
자격은 다 갖추셨나요???
a profiler needs.
프로파일러가 필요합니다.
First, your refusal to give up.
첫째, 포기를 거부하는 것입니다.
-All detectives-- -You also have an open mind.
-탐정 여러분-- -너도 마음이 열려 있구나.
Intuition, general knowledge, and the skill to analyze logically.
직관력, 일반 지식, 논리적으로 분석하는 능력입니다.
And also a detachment of personal feelings.
그리고 개인적인 감정의 분리도 있습니다 .
But more important than all that…
하지만 그보다 더 중요한 것은???
The thing I find most important is sensitivity.
제가 가장 중요하게 생각하는 것은 감성입니다.
"Sensitivity"?
"감광도"?
Would it be easier to understand if I say sensitivity towards others?
타인을 향한 감수성을 말하면 이해하기 쉬울까요 ?
Why would you need that?
그게 왜 필요하겠어요?
Because it's a job that analyzes people's minds.
사람의 마음을 분석하는 직업이니까 .
Goodness. You only say the most confusing things.
선량. 가장 혼란스러운 말만 하더군요 .
Hey, take this.
야, 이거 받아.
Give it a read when you have time.
시간이 나면 한번 읽어보세요.
And have some of these when you have time.
그리고 시간이 있을 때 이것들 중 일부를 드십시오.
Thank you. What is this?
감사합니다. 이게 뭔가요?
I'm making an attempt to form a new team.
새로운 팀을 구성하려고 노력 중이에요.
I think I found the right guy…
내가 맞는 사람을 찾은 것 같아???
as a criminal behavioral analyst.
범죄 행동 분석가로서.
It's the perfect job for someone like you.
당신 같은 사람에게 딱 맞는 직업이에요.
I'm fine with what I do now.
나는 지금 내가 하는 일에 괜찮다.
Hey, if you turn me down just like that, you'll hurt my feelings.
야, 그렇게 거절하면 내 마음이 상할 것 같아.
It's tough to tell…
말하기 힘들죠???
what you're thinking.
당신이 생각하는 것.
But that's also a strength for a profiler.
하지만 이는 프로파일러의 강점이기도 합니다.
Are you teasing me?
나를 놀리는 거야?
No, I'm very serious.
아니요, 저는 매우 심각합니다.
You don't have to decide right away.
당장 결정할 필요는 없습니다.
It'll take some time to make the team.
팀을 구성하는 데 시간이 좀 걸릴 것입니다.
But for now, just remember that there is
하지만 지금은
something like this.
이 같은.
Where do you think you're going?
어디로 갈 것 같나요?
You knocked her out. Then what?
당신이 그녀를 쓰러뜨렸어요. 그리고 뭐?
Yes, you got on top of her.
네, 당신이 그 사람 위에 올라탔어요.
And strangled her, right?
그리고 목을 졸랐지, 그렇지?
How did you do it?
넌 어떻게 그걸 했니?
SUSPECT
용의자
Her neck.
그녀의 목.
You strangled her, right?
당신이 그 사람을 목졸라 죽였죠?
Man, this guy is driving me insane.
아, 이 사람이 나를 미치게 만들고 있어요.
Hey, your hands weren't like that.
야, 네 손은 그렇지 않았어.
You pushed your hands up to her chin and strangled her.
당신은 그녀의 턱에 손을 대고 목을 졸라 죽였습니다.
Start pressing.
누르기 시작하세요.
You did this, so why don't you remember?
당신이 이런 일을 했는데 왜 기억하지 못하는 걸까요?
Do it.
해.
We're running out of time. Hurry up.
시간이 부족해요. 서둘러요.
Keep taking the video.
계속 영상을 찍으세요.
After you strangled her, what's next?
그녀를 목졸라 죽인 후 다음은 뭐죠?
And then what? You unbuttoned her shirt.
그 다음엔? 당신은 그녀의 셔츠 단추를 풀었습니다.
Take her clothes off.
그녀의 옷을 벗으세요.
-Why did you kill your girlfriend? -All right.
-왜 여자친구를 죽였나요? -괜찮은.
Tell us the motive of your murder!
살인 동기를 알려주세요!
Bring my daughter back!
내 딸을 다시 데려오세요!
The victim lost her irreplaceable and precious life
그 무엇과도 바꿀 수 없는 소중한 생명을 잃은 피해자
at such a young age.
너무 어린 나이에
It is clear the victim's family will live in pain
피해자 가족이 고통 속에 살게 될 것은 분명하다
for the rest of her life, along with a psychological shock.
평생 동안 심리적 충격을 받았습니다.
The crime of taking another person's life
타인의 생명을 빼앗는 범죄
is serious and unacceptable.
심각하고 용납할 수 없는 일입니다.
And the accused did not reflect on his crime
그리고 피고인은 자신의 범행을 반성하지 않았습니다
despite his history of assault.
폭행 이력에도 불구하고
It was concluded that his crime was heinous.
그의 범죄는 극악무도하다고 결론이 내려졌습니다 .
Hence, the court sentences Bang Ki-hoon, the accused,
따라서 법원은 피고인 방기훈에게 형을 선고합니다.
to 12 years in prison.
12년 징역
INVESTIGATION RECORD CASE CLOSED
조사 기록 사건이 종결됨
North Korea test-fired a new ballistic missile today.
북한이 오늘 신형 탄도미사일을 시험발사했습니다.
Today at 5:40 p.m., with the sound of a foghorn,
오늘 오후 5시 40분, 무적나팔 소리와 함께
a historic departure was made for Mount Geumgang…
금강산으로의 역사적인 출발 ???
The EU's unified currency, Euro,
EU의 통합 통화인 유로
was launched to unite the 300 million Europeans
3억 유럽인을 통합하기 위해 출범했습니다
into one economic bloc.
하나의 경제 블록으로
Sin Chang-won was finally caught.
신창원이 드디어 잡혔습니다.
The escape of the century, starring Sin Chang-won,
신창원 주연의 세기의 탈출
came to an end this afternoon thanks to a civilian's report.
민간인의 신고로 오늘 오후에 끝났습니다 .
Let's hear more about this story
이 이야기에 대해 더 자세히 들어보세요
from Reporter Choi Yong-beom.
최용범 기자입니다.
Believe in Christ, go to heaven.
그리스도를 믿고 천국에 가세요.
Disbelief will send you to hell.
불신은 당신을 지옥으로 보낼 것입니다.
Believe in Christ,
그리스도를 믿으세요
and you shall go to heaven.
그리고 당신은 천국에 갈 것입니다.
If you do not, you'll be sent to hell.
그렇지 않으면 당신은 지옥에 보내질 것입니다.
Believe in Christ…
그리스도를 믿으세요???
The police…
경찰???
I'm back.
나는 돌아왔다.
-You brought it back? -Goodness, you didn't have to.
- 다시 가져왔나요? - 맙소사, 그럴 필요는 없었어요.
It didn't take long.
오래 걸리지 않았습니다.
Good work, Kang-moo. You should go home.
수고했어, 강무야. 집에 가야 해.
Thank you, sir.
감사합니다.
-Good work today. -Good work.
-오늘 수고했어. -잘 했어.
Take good care of your grandma.
할머니를 잘 보살펴주세요.
-Okay. Goodbye. -Bye.
-좋아요. 안녕히 가세요. -안녕.
He's very diligent, unlike other kids these days.
요즘 다른 아이들과 달리 굉장히 부지런해요 .
I hope my son can be half the man Kang-moo is.
내 아들이 강무의 절반이 되기를 바랍니다 .
Teens these days are all like your kid.
요즘 십대들은 모두 당신의 아이와 같습니다.
He's the odd one out.
그 사람은 정말 이상한 사람이에요.
Whenever he gets paid,
그가 돈을 받을 때마다
he takes it to his grandmother.
그는 그것을 할머니에게 가져갑니다.
There's no kid like him these days.
요즘엔 그런 애가 없어요
Does he think he's my dad or what?
그 사람이 자기가 내 아빠라고 생각하는 걸까요?
SUNGWON RESTAURANT
성원식당
STAY TUNED FOR THE EPILOGUE
에필로그를 계속 지켜봐주세요
Ha-young, what did you do with your friends today?
하영아 오늘 친구들이랑 뭐했어 ?
This lady looks sad.
이 여자는 슬퍼 보인다.
-Yes. -Why is she sad?
-예. -왜 슬픈가요?
Do you know how scary it is
얼마나 무서운지 아시나요?
when you're deep underwater?
물속에 깊이 있을 때?
YOUNGSHIN SUPERMARKET
영신슈퍼마켓
She must've been scared and sad.
무서웠고 슬펐을 것 같아요.
Her mom isn't there in the water.
그녀의 엄마는 물 속에 없습니다.
Ha-young.
하영.
Come here.
이리 오세요.
It's not that Ha-young isn't sympathetic.
하영이가 동정심이 없는 건 아니다.
He's very sympathetic.
그는 매우 동정적입니다.
I'm not sure if you'll understand.
당신이 이해할 수 있을지 모르겠습니다.
But he can look deeply into people's inner sides.
하지만 그는 사람의 내면을 깊이 들여다볼 수 있다.
Their inner sides?
그들의 내면은?
Ha-young. What about your umbrella?
하영. 당신의 우산은 어떻습니까?
I gave you an umbrella this morning.
오늘 아침에는 내가 너에게 우산을 줬어.
Where is it?
어디입니까?
Ha-young is only nine years old.
하영은 이제 겨우 9살이다.
It's because he's a child.
어린아이이기 때문이죠.
He sees a difference between his feelings and other people's reactions.
그는 자신의 감정 과 다른 사람들의 반응 사이의 차이를 봅니다 .
He must have realized that he is different from others.
그는 자신이 남들과 다르다는 것을 깨달았을 것입니다 .
Seeing the dead body that day…
그날 시체를 봤나요???
triggered this thought in his head.
그의 머릿속에 이런 생각이 촉발되었습니다.
So he's trying to hide his emotions.
그래서 그는 자신의 감정을 숨기려고 노력하고 있는 것입니다.
Don't worry, Ha-young.
걱정하지 마세요, 하영님.
I will bury it in a nice place.
좋은 곳에 묻어둘게요.
Come here.
이리 오세요.
I want to know why you thought he didn't do it.
왜 그가 그렇게 하지 않았다고 생각했는지 알고 싶습니다 .
If you don't catch him, it'll happen again.
그 사람을 잡지 못하면 이런 일이 또 일어날 거예요.
Detective Song of Dongbu Police Station went to Yang Yong-chul,
동부경찰서 송형사가 양용철을 찾아갔고,
an inmate in prison, and received help from him.
감옥에 수감되어 그로부터 도움을 받았습니다.
This news shocked the public.
이 소식은 대중에게 충격을 주었습니다.
That a detective keeps visiting him and asking him for advice!
탐정이 계속 그를 찾아와 조언을 구한다는 사실!
Criminals understand each other better.
범죄자들은 ​​서로를 더 잘 이해합니다.
I think we can finally form the Behavioral Analysis Team.
드디어 행동분석팀을 구성할 수 있을 것 같아요 .
Others couldn't understand, but you instinctively knew this was necessary.
다른 사람들은 이해할 수 없었지만 당신은 본능적으로 이것이 필요하다는 것을 알았습니다.
I'm certain that you're the perfect person for this job.
나는 당신이 이 일에 완벽한 사람 이라고 확신합니다 .